<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kevin Webber</title>
    <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kevin Webber</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://rocketpages.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Streams: The Glue of the Real-Time Organization</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/deck/reactive-streams-glue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/deck/reactive-streams-glue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;real-time organization&amp;rdquo; reacts to information now rather than basing critical decisions on stale data. This requires reimagining how data flows through your organization, moving away from data at rest and moving towards a completely event-based streaming architecture. Events become the lifeblood of the organization, while analytics becomes the brain. Organizations that successfully harness the power of real-time event streaming can transform analytical latencies from hours to seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session will describe a reference architecture using the Lightbend Reactive Platform and other tools that can be used to build out the real-time organization, leveraging real-time data to produce analytics that result in immediate, actionable insights.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Streams: The Glue of the Real-time Organization</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/talk/2016-03-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/talk/2016-03-21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articles on Medium</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The articles below cover technical subjects in depth, focusing on areas of distributed systems such as &lt;em&gt;reactive programming&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;event-based architectures&lt;/em&gt;. The articles below have accumulated well over 100,000 views since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of blog posts and personal anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/home/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/home/intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a systems analyst, architect, developer, and technical speaker from Toronto, Canada. I specialize in systems modernization, reactive programming, and developer productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work as the global &lt;em&gt;Enterprise Advocate&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lightbend.com&#34;&gt;Lightbend&lt;/a&gt; (formerly Typesafe), the corporate entity behind the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language, &lt;a href=&#34;http://akka.io/&#34;&gt;Akka&lt;/a&gt; distributed systems framework, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.playframework.com/&#34;&gt;Play&lt;/a&gt; web framework, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lightbend.com/lagom&#34;&gt;Lagom&lt;/a&gt; microservices framework. In this role I work as an analyst and advisor to major enterprises - commonly referred to as the Global 2000 by Forbes - on systems modernization projects using the principles of &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/reactive-programming/what-is-reactive-programming-bc9fa7f4a7fc#.lpdqdjp72&#34;&gt;reactive programming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resume</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/resume/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning more about any area of expertise listed below, please &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/forms/Ox9cGw4Ohw&#34;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to meet over Skype or in-person in downtown Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlights:c59a67a3c7bc5faa453847420267045e&#34;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over 15 years of development and architecture experience&lt;/strong&gt; — Significant experience within the JVM and Java ecosystem, having performed the role of architect, analyst, technical leader, developer, and advocate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experienced public speaker&lt;/strong&gt; — Presenting at meetups, conferences, and to private businesses around the world about modern software development, architecture, and process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proficient technical writer&lt;/strong&gt; — Regularly contributing to various publications such as Medium, InfoQ, and TechRepublic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills:c59a67a3c7bc5faa453847420267045e&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modernization&lt;/strong&gt; — Acting as an advisory architect for systems modernization projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; — Domain-Driven Design (DDD), OOA/D, distributed systems architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Languages&lt;/strong&gt; — Scala, Java, JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frameworks&lt;/strong&gt; — Play, Akka, Spring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DevOps&lt;/strong&gt; — Vagrant, Puppet, Kubernetes, ConductR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ops&lt;/strong&gt; — Implementing cloud and hybrid-cloud topologies for clustered, scalable, resilient systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;areas-of-interest:c59a67a3c7bc5faa453847420267045e&#34;&gt;Areas of interest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modernization&lt;/strong&gt; of legacy systems to &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;distributed systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming&lt;/strong&gt; in hybrid object-oriented and functional style using &lt;em&gt;Scala&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; of non-trivial systems; solving the hard problems using emerging patterns to build event-driven, reactive systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stream processing&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;em&gt;Akka Streams&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spark&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Kafka&lt;/em&gt;, especially related to batch/ETL modernization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalable, resilient web systems development&lt;/strong&gt; using &lt;em&gt;Play&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Akka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conferences, meetups, webinars, and companies that have kindly hosted one of my talks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Videos</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Presentations and educational videos on mostly technical subjects, with a few personal vlogs thrown into the mix. If you have any ideas for future content, please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinars</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/webinars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 15:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/webinars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a regular presenter for Lightbend, touching on subjects from microservices to enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modernizing your Monolith with Microservices</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/webinar/legacy-java-monolith/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/webinar/legacy-java-monolith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We walk through 6 key architectural concepts to understand before embarking on a microservices modernization project. No experience with microservices or distributed systems necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 6 Rules for Modernizing your Aging Java Monolith with Microservices</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/talk/2016-03-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/talk/2016-03-10/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How does a compiler, interpreter, and CPU work?</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e2-compiler-interpreter-cpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e2-compiler-interpreter-cpu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video we discuss how compilers, interpreters, and CPUs transform source code written by computers programmers into machine code, and how the CPU executes machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software is Eating the World</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e1-software-is-eating-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e1-software-is-eating-the-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first video from All Aboot Software, a new non-profit educational channel about software and technology. In this video we discuss the profound change software is having on business and society, framed around Marc Andreeseen&amp;rsquo;s famous 2011 quote that &amp;ldquo;software is eating the world&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/photo/thomson-reuters/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/photo/thomson-reuters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Speaking at Thomson Reuters about Reactive Streams.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diving into Akka Streams</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/article/diving-into-akka-streams/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/article/diving-into-akka-streams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Akka Streams is a toolkit for per-event processing of streams. It’s an implementation of the Reactive Streams specification, which promises interoperability between a variety of compliant streaming libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking in events enables us to rethink our systems in a purely reactive way — ingesting events, issuing commands which emit new events. We can feed those events back into our system, or emit them for further downstream processing. Forward thinking organizations are using event-driven architectures like this to transform batch-mode systems into real-time systems, reducing latencies from hours to seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>