<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Videos on Kevin Webber</title>
    <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Videos on Kevin Webber</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://rocketpages.github.io/video/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Enterprise Architect&#39;s Intro To Microservices</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/enterprise-arch-msa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/enterprise-arch-msa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We review the history of application development, from the early days of monoliths and SOA to the emergence of microservice architectures. Then we dive into microservices architecture (MSA) and compare it against service-oriented architectures (SOA).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modernizing your Monolith with Microservices</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/legacy-java-monolith/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/legacy-java-monolith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We walk through 6 key architectural concepts to understand before embarking on a microservices modernization project. No experience with microservices or distributed systems necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How does a compiler, interpreter, and CPU work?</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e2-compiler-interpreter-cpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e2-compiler-interpreter-cpu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video we discuss how compilers, interpreters, and CPUs transform source code written by computers programmers into machine code, and how the CPU executes machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software is Eating the World</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e1-software-is-eating-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/e1-software-is-eating-the-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first video from All Aboot Software, a new non-profit educational channel about software and technology. In this video we discuss the profound change software is having on business and society, framed around Marc Andreeseen&amp;rsquo;s famous 2011 quote that &amp;ldquo;software is eating the world&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revitalizing Aging Architectures with Microservices</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/revitalized-with-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/revitalized-with-microservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a long-version talk of my session at Gartner AADI in Las Vegas; Lessons Learned: Revitalizing Walmart&amp;rsquo;s Aging Architecture For Web Scale. It includes added content and runs at 60 minutes instead of 30, giving us time to elaborate on various architectural patterns and considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revitalizing Walmart&#39;s Aging Architecture For Web Scale</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/gartner-aadi-walmart-web-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/gartner-aadi-walmart-web-scale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story of how Walmart Canada revitalized its aging architecture with a microservices model built for speed and performance - that efficiently leveraged its JVM infrastructure - to achieve major e-commerce success in just 12 months: Conversions up 20%; Mobile orders up 98%; No downtime during Black Friday or Boxing Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forrester: What Architects Need To Know About Going Reactive</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/forrester-going-reactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/forrester-going-reactive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A joint webinar with Michael Facemire, Principal Analyst at Forrester Research. We discuss how to leverage a Reactive architectural model to ensure your back-end infrastructure isn’t the limiting factor for your business success.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Dive into the Typesafe Reactive Platform</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/play-activator-deep-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/play-activator-deep-dive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting started with the Play framework for web development. We cover Activator as a tool for learning, building, and exploring projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go Reactive! Reactive web application development with Scala, Play, and Akka</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/go-reactive-geecon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/go-reactive-geecon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll cover patterns and techniques for building responsive user interfaces, continuing down through an end-to-end reference web architecture in Scala and Play to demonstrate how to build responsive, resilient, and elastic web applications. In our demonstrations Akka will provide a message-driven core in order to support the entire stack by enabling the distribution of work to local and remote workers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Reactive Programming?</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/what-is-reactive-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/what-is-reactive-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exploring the principles and history of reactive programming in order to frame it for a modern context. Presented at ReactiveTO on July 24, 2014. Inspired by talks by Joe Armstrong and Jonas Bonér.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enterprise Web Development with Play and Scala</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/play-all-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/video/play-all-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The talk will cover strategies to help integrate Play with complex ecosystems and other enterprise development challenges. The secondary objective is to assist designing Play applications that are developed by multiple, distributed, cross-functional teams.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>