<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Kevin Webber</title>
    <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Kevin Webber</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 21:54:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://rocketpages.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Start a Consulting Company</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/how-to-start-a-consulting-company/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 21:54:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/how-to-start-a-consulting-company/</guid>
      <description>Last fall I decided to leave Lightbend to pursue a dream that I&amp;rsquo;ve had for the better part of a decade: starting a consulting company. So, in late 2016, RedElastic was born.
Starting RedElastic is the hardest, most rewarding, and most exciting things I&amp;rsquo;ve done in my life. Every experience that I&amp;rsquo;ve had up until now, both professionally and personally, has lead up to the point that starting RedElastic wasn&amp;rsquo;t even up for debate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye, Lightbend</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/goodbye-lightbend/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/goodbye-lightbend/</guid>
      <description>It’s been an incredible two-and-a-half years.
My journey to Lightbend began after an incredible experience as an early customer of Typesafe. I began using the Typesafe stack — Scala, Play, and Akka — in 2012 to help deliver the revamped Walmart Canada consumer platform. It was a fantastic project that afforded our team a tremendous opportunity; to help bring the techniques of reactive programming to one of the biggest companies in the world and to millions of customers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Zen of Process</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-zen-of-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-zen-of-process/</guid>
      <description>Process improvements are the most impactful way to rise above your individual work. All organizations live and die by the quality of their processes.
 “Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe.” — Abraham Lincoln
 Have you ever wondered how an organization with tens of thousands of people survives without collapsing under its own weight? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t survive by hiring &amp;ldquo;only hire the best&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on Reactive Systems</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/reflecting-on-reactive-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/reflecting-on-reactive-systems/</guid>
      <description>The past year has been a wonderful period of learning and reflection on this exciting new software architecture. I’ve written about reactive application development on Medium (What is Reactive Programming?), contributed to ReadWrite (&amp;ldquo;Reactive&amp;rdquo; Systems: Easy To Program, Now Easier To Manage), and contributed to InfoQ (Actor-based Concurrency for Reactive Systems).
Another high note is that Reactive Programming Toronto is closing in on 300 members. New reactive programming groups are forming all over the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retrospective: A Night of Reactive Programming</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/retrospective-a-night-of-reactive-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/retrospective-a-night-of-reactive-programming/</guid>
      <description>I hosted the first event for ReactiveTO on July 24th. It was fantastic evening filled with great talks on reactive programming principles, microservices, Akka, and ReactiveCocoa.
Impressions It was wonderful to see so many folks show up with interest in such a wide variety of languages and toolkits. We had developers representing the communities of JavaScript (Node.js), Ruby (EventMachine), Objective-C (ReactiveCocoa), and Scala (Akka), among many other languages and toolkits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agile and Waterfall can live together in harmony</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/agile-and-waterfall-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/agile-and-waterfall-together/</guid>
      <description>Agile is challenging to use on certain projects, like those bound by fixed-price, fixed-date contracts. Agencies, governments, and other organizations who are bound by contracts struggle to implement Agile effectively. Contracts force software developers to adopt less flexible approaches to development in order to satisfy negotiated requirements and deadlines. Even worse than taking an alternate approach is to use the wrong approach entirely. This can manifest itself as a completely bastardized version of Agile, which is unfortunately the most common version in use today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Git, Part 3: Moving your code to Git</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-3-moving-your-code-to-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-3-moving-your-code-to-git/</guid>
      <description>This is the third and final part in a three part series about migrating to Git. I recommend reading part one and part two if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already. Migrating to Git is worth it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a trivial decision.
Migrating to Git, Part 1: Advantages
Migrating to Git, Part 2: Prerequisites
If you&amp;rsquo;re ready to proceed with a migration to Git, congratulations! You&amp;rsquo;re about to start using one of the best development tools available today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Git, Part 2: Prerequisites</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-2-prerequisites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-2-prerequisites/</guid>
      <description>This is the second part of a three part series about migrating to Git. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read part one and are unfamiliar with the advantages of Git, you should check it out.
Migrating to Git, Part 1: Advantages
If you already understand the benefits of Git, or have already read part one, welcome to part two in the series! We&amp;rsquo;re going to discuss certain pre-conditions of a migration to Git and make sure your team is ready for the transition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Git, Part 1: Advantages</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-1-advantages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/migrating-to-git-part-1-advantages/</guid>
      <description>Git is unlike typical version control systems. Sure, Git is used to version files, but how is that any different than SVN or SourceSafe or ClearCase?
Git expects developers to understand how it works under the hood. It expects developers to be comfortable with the command line to get the most out of it. It provides very little in the way of convention and expects you to design your own workflow simply by using it as another tool in your arsenal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joy at QCon New York</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/joy-at-qcon-new-york/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/joy-at-qcon-new-york/</guid>
      <description>I recently travelled to New York City to attend QCon.
Joy isn&amp;rsquo;t the typical emotion that comes to mind when one pictures enterprise software and enterprise software developers, but technical culture is changing rapidly and more people are recognizing the business value of joy.
It&amp;rsquo;s an exciting time to be a software developer.
A decade ago we watched a grim-faced Peter Gibbons in the movie Office Space commiserate about his mind-numbing job of churning out Y2K patches for the cold and heartless Initech Corporation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiplayer tic-tac-toe in Java using the WebSocket API, Netty (NIO), and jQuery</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/multiplayer-tic-tac-toe-in-java-using-the-websocket-api-netty-nio-and-jquery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/multiplayer-tic-tac-toe-in-java-using-the-websocket-api-netty-nio-and-jquery/</guid>
      <description>What does this game of tic-tac-toe and Twitter have in common? Both have been implemented using relatively the same technologies: Java and Netty. It was big news in 2010 when Twitter migrated their search from Ruby on Rails to Java-based Netty (read about it here). Not only was it big in the news department, but it was also big in the results department: Twitter reported their search performance increased by 3x.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing Fancybox with AJAX (and Wicket)</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/fixing-fancybox-with-ajax-and-wicket/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/fixing-fancybox-with-ajax-and-wicket/</guid>
      <description>A personal project I&amp;rsquo;m working on uses the jQuery Fancybox library to display images. It&amp;rsquo;s a great lightbox, except for one small problem: AJAX refreshes break it.
A page I&amp;rsquo;m working on accepts multiple image uploads. Once the images are successfully processed asynchronously on the server, an image panel on the same page is automatically refreshed. The AJAX callback works fine and updates the panel view with the newly uploaded photos, but the net result is that Fancybox stops working completely.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connection pooling with Hibernate 3.3.x and C3P0</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/connection-pooling-with-hibernate-3-3-x-and-c3p0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/connection-pooling-with-hibernate-3-3-x-and-c3p0/</guid>
      <description>Hibernate uses it&amp;rsquo;s own built-in connection pool out of the box. There are some pretty heavy duty sites running with the default connection pool enabled in production despite the obvious warning against doing this.
INFO DriverManagerConnectionProvider:64 - Using Hibernate built-in connection pool (not for production use!) INFO DriverManagerConnectionProvider:65 - Hibernate connection pool size: 1  A few minor problems creep up with this default configuration left alone, such as the inability for Hibernate to reconnect closed connections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Java</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/beyond-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/beyond-java/</guid>
      <description>A recent post by Mike Gualtieri of Forrester caught my attention. Mike strongly asserts that Java is a dead end for enterprises and business software should be built with something else. Mike mentions a few different options, but mainly promotes 4GL tools such as Powerbuilder and “all in one” business infrastructure software such as SoftwareAG webMethods. He also touches on BPM and event processing, and by event processing I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure he means CEP tools such as Esper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future of Java in the enterprise</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-future-of-java-in-the-enterprise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-future-of-java-in-the-enterprise/</guid>
      <description>It’s been a busy few years in the Java world. Oracle’s acquisition of Sun is obviously the largest piece of news and has a significant impact on the future of Java. Oracle’s new position as owner and commander-in-chief now places Java squarely in the enterprise realm alongside Oracle’s other products. Java has always been an enterprise technology, but without the JCP promoting collaborative innovation, who knows what kind of traction Java would have made in the world?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Desire paths</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/desire-paths/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/desire-paths/</guid>
      <description>A desire path is what a person wants rather than what an architect builds. The term desire path originated from landscape architecture, but it&amp;rsquo;s an increasingly important concept for software architects to grasp. If you understand desire paths, you understand the future of software development.
A desire path represents the evolutionary nature of how people interact with their environment. An engineer designs a concrete path, but people find it more convenient to create their own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The greatest line of code ever</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-greatest-line-of-code-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/the-greatest-line-of-code-ever/</guid>
      <description>if (statusIsNotValid.compareTo( Boolean.FALSE ) != 0) skipValidation = false;  If you ever find yourself working in a team that doesn&amp;rsquo;t see the importance of code reviews, remind them that they could easily wind up with a few million lines of that.
(Taken from The Daily WTF.)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Uploadify with Java using Apache Wicket</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/integrating-uploadify-with-java-using-apache-wicket/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/integrating-uploadify-with-java-using-apache-wicket/</guid>
      <description>One of the most requested features on any site that accepts file submissions is the ability to handle multiple uploads elegantly. The current HTML standard only permits one file upload at a time, which makes transferring a large number of files quite tedious.
This tutorial will show how to painlessly integrate Uploadify and Java using Apache Wicket. You should have at least beginner-level knowledge of Wicket before moving forward, but feel free to dive right in even if you&amp;rsquo;ve never used Wicket before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be a Revolutionary</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/be-a-revolutionary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/be-a-revolutionary/</guid>
      <description>Good developers always strive to become better. We spend time searching for the perfect language, the perfect framework, the perfect IDE, the perfect testing tool, the perfect methodology.
Building great software requires all of these things, albeit nothing is perfect. There is no perfect methodology, language, or tool. At times we focus so much on the most complex things that we forget how to do the most simple things, like designing software that people actually enjoy using.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apache Aries: OSGi for the Enterprise</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/apache-aries-osgi-for-the-enterprise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/apache-aries-osgi-for-the-enterprise/</guid>
      <description>I recently came across a blog post about an Apache project called Aries, currently in incubator status. You can check out the details here. It looks like enterprise developers are in for a real treat: the missing secret sauce that allows enterprise application developers to harness the goodness of OSGi.
 Aries will offer an enterprise OSGi application programming model that enables applications to leverage Java EE and other enterprise technologies and to benefit from the modularity, dynamism and versioning capabilities of OSGi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t forget team structure</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/dont-forget-team-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/dont-forget-team-structure/</guid>
      <description>In the summer I blogged about SOA and wondered out loud if true SOA was impossible to implement in some organizations due to the organizational structure itself. Janie Chang at Microsoft Research wrote an excellent article that touched on the subject. To quote Janie:
 The system will resemble the organization building the system.
 I agree with this assertion completely. Team culture and structure can vary widely even within the same organization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is SOA doomed?</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/is-soa-doomed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/is-soa-doomed/</guid>
      <description>Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, I think the spirit of SOA is fantastic. Adaptable, flexible, maintainable, loosely-coupled applications supported by open governance, strong relationships between business and technology folks, and co-operation across all silos and levels of an organization. What&amp;rsquo;s not to love?
SOA has become one of the most commonly-heard buzzwords around the water-cooler over the past few years. It seems like everyone is talking about SOA these days. Architects, developers, business folks, management, non-management, and everyone in-between.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>